<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors | The M.A.D. lab</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Authors</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Julien GA Martin</copyright>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu7d068ed1bf5378934f15b005350ee472_16136_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <link>/authors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alex Jebb</title>
      <link>/author/alex-jebb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/author/alex-jebb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alex is interested in the effects of early-life or maternal environment on the life histories of individuals within a species. She is will be researching this by comparing and contrasting different hypotheses, such as the Silver Spoon Hypothesis and Predictive Adaptive Response Hypothesis, within a long-term study population of Yellow-bellied Marmots in Colorado, U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During her PhD, Alex was co-supervised by Pierre Bize and Julien Martin.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bennett Krasnay</title>
      <link>/author/bennett-krasnay/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/author/bennett-krasnay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am using a quantitative genetic method to evaluate heritability of longevity within and between sexes in Yellow Bellied Marmots. This project features data from a long-term database on marmot life history traits collected at the Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory in Colorado. I hope to branch out and explore different branches of evolutionary and comparative biology in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mairi Young</title>
      <link>/author/mairi-young/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/author/mairi-young/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;​&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serena Spallin</title>
      <link>/author/serena-spallin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/author/serena-spallin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Project description&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sol Milne</title>
      <link>/author/sol-milne/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/author/sol-milne/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sol Milne uses drones to study the ecology of orangutans and phenological activity of tropical forest. He is currently studying the effect of different land uses on Orangutan population densities forests of in Sabah, Malaysia which are strongly affected by logging and agroforestry practices. He is also using citizen science based identification of orangutan nests from drone images to determine population densities across different land use types. My zooniverse project should be available soon on the official zooniverse website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During his PhD, Sol was co-supervised by David Burslem (uAberdeen) and Julien Martin&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sophie St. Lawrence</title>
      <link>/author/sophie-st.-lawrence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/author/sophie-st.-lawrence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;​
I am interested in how climate change, specifically increasing mean spring temperatures, is impacting the evolution of and change in the timing of reproduction and its plasticity in yellow-bellied marmots. I will be conducting this study using a long-term dataset on yellow-bellied marmots colected at the Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory (RMBL), Colorado, USA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yasmeen Hichri</title>
      <link>/author/yasmeen-hichri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/author/yasmeen-hichri/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Project description&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
