<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>marmots | The M.A.D. lab</title>
    <link>/tag/marmots/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/marmots/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>marmots</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Julien GA Martin</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu7d068ed1bf5378934f15b005350ee472_16136_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>marmots</title>
      <link>/tag/marmots/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome new students</title>
      <link>/posts/2021-09-10-welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/2021-09-10-welcome/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/posts/2021-09-10-welcome/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Welcome new students in the lab:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 MSc students&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Émilie Gagnon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carol-Ann Chabot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 honors students&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bernadette Chan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mayra Monir&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maryam Musso-Bello&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serena Spallin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yasmeen Hichri&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 MSc and 1 PhD available</title>
      <link>/posts/2021-02-18-grad_position/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/2021-02-18-grad_position/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/posts/2021-02-18-grad_position/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have 3 positions graduate positions available in my lab on evolutionary ecology and behavioural ecology
of marmots and manatees.
Please see &lt;a href=&#34;/opportunities&#34;&gt;Opportunities&lt;/a&gt; for more details&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MSc in evolutionary ecology</title>
      <link>/opportunities/opp_past/2021-02-18-mscmarmots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/opportunities/opp_past/2021-02-18-mscmarmots/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/opportunities/opp_past/2021-02-18-mscmarmots/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;YBmarmot.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;project&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life-histories strategies are strongly influenced by environmental conditions and age. To understand the how animals adapt and evolve in natural conditions, it is key to understand how life-history trade-offs vary throughout the life of individuals. The main aim of the project will be to investigate variation in life-history trade-offs with environment age and/or sexes variation using the yellow-bellied marmot long-term study (&amp;gt; 50 years). The richness of the study system will allow the student to further define the project at the beginning of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will be supervised by Pr. Julien Martin (uOttawa). The project will be done in collaboration with Pr. Dan Blumstein (UCLA, USA) and the Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory, RMBL, USA. The student will be based at the Biology department of the University of Ottawa and will participate to field work in Colorado at RMBL during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;financial-support&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Financial support&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Available for 2 years. The student is expected to complete a minimum of two teaching assistantship per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;starting-date&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Starting date&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally September 2021 or January 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;candidate-profile&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Candidate Profile&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideal candidate should have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BSc in biology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A strong interest for statistical analyses and R programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to work alone and in teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A willingness to work in French and in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-apply&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to apply&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students that are interested should send by email to Julien Martin (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:julien.martin@uottawa.ca&#34; class=&#34;email&#34;&gt;julien.martin@uottawa.ca&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a writing sample (thesis, paper or scientific article),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a CV, a motivation letter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the contact of two references&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a copy of their transcripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;YBmarmot.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phd in evolutionary ecology</title>
      <link>/opportunities/opp_past/2021-02-18-phdmarmots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/opportunities/opp_past/2021-02-18-phdmarmots/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/opportunities/opp_past/2021-02-18-phdmarmots/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;YBmarmot.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;project&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most model of evolution consider that intra-individual variance, once corrected for environmental variation, is essentially random noise and is similar across individuals. However, recent studies in captivity showed that within-individual variance could in fact have a genetic basis. In addition, several studies on captive animal have shown the evolutionary importance of the genetic variance in individual variation. For examples, animal breeding try to select for milking cows with low daily variation in milk production to facilitate stock prediction and management. So if we start to understand the importance and the interest of the genetic basis of within-individual variation in breeding programs, the evolutionary importance of this genetic component remain relatively unknown in the wild. Consequently, to better understand evolution in the wild it is key to evaluate the existence and quantify the amount of genetic variance in the intra-individual variance of traits and how it correlates with other traits including fitness. Ideally to get a wider understanding of the phenomenon, such study would need to look at multiple type of traits and across multiple species. Since this has rarely been done, to get a better understanding this needs to be evaluated across multiple traits and species. The aim of this project is to used new quantitative genetic models, a statistical approach allowing to estimate the genetic variance in a trait in wild population, to quantify the genetic variation in within-individual variance in multiple traits across at least 5 species using long-term pedigreed natural populations including yellow-bellied marmots, alpine swifts, eastern chipmunks, bighorn sheep and red squirrels. The project will thus be based on over 150 years of field work (combined across all species). This project will offer opportunity to learn a variety of important methods in evolutionary biology and to participate in the field work on the marmot system. The student will be given a thorough training in field skills and in statistical modelling to tease apart the amount of trait variance explained by genetic and environmental effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;relevant-publications&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Relevant publications&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prentice PM, Houslay TM, Martin JGA, Wilson AJ. 2020 Genetic variance for behavioural ‘predictability’ of stress response. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 33, 642–652.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martin JGA et al. 2017. Genetic basis of between- and within-individual variance of docility. Journal of Evolutionary Biology, 30(4):796-805.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Westneat DF, Wright J, Dingemanse NJ. 2015 The biology hidden inside residual within-individual phenotypic variation. Biological Reviews 90, 729–743.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;affiliation-and-life&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Affiliation and life&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will be supervised by &lt;strong&gt;Pr. Julien Martin (uOttawa)&lt;/strong&gt;. The project will be done in collaborations with the project leaders of participating long-term studies. The student will be based at the Biology department of the University of Ottawa. He/she will have the opportunity to perform field work over the summer in Colorado on the yellow-bellied marmot long-term study and to visit project leaders in Canada (Ottawa, Montreal, Sherbrooke, Edmonton), United-States (Los-Angeles, Boulder) and United-Kingdom (Aberdeen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ottawa consistently ranks among the best Canadian cities. You’ll love an easy-going lifestyle that appeals to urban adventurers and nature lovers alike. Enjoy a revitalized city that is bursting with energy. Gigs, festivals, theatre and art are all close by in a walkable downtown core. And, having the 2nd highest concentration of scientists and engineers in North America, you’ll have lots of opportunities to build up your network and kick-start your career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;financial-support&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Financial support&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Financial support is available for 4 years. The student is expected to complete two teaching assistantship per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;starting-date&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Starting date&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally September 2021 or January 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;candidate-profile&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Candidate Profile&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this PhD project our ideal candidate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has a MSc in biology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is creative, highly motivated and can work alone or in teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has strong interest in evolutionary biology and quantitative genetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has strong interest for statistical analyses and past experience with R programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-apply&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to apply&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students that are interested should send by email to Julien Martin (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:julien.martin@uottawa.ca&#34; class=&#34;email&#34;&gt;julien.martin@uottawa.ca&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a writing sample (thesis, paper or scientific article),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a CV, a motivation letter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the contact of two references&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a copy of their transcripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;YBmarmot.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research projects</title>
      <link>/project/old_page/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/old_page/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;main-projects&#34;&gt;Main projects&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;senescence-in-yellow-bellied-marmots&#34;&gt;Senescence in yellow-bellied marmots&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus of this project is to teae apart age-dependent and age-independent effects of senescence and determine their interactions with environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;evolution-and-environmental-change-in-yellow-bellied-marmots&#34;&gt;Evolution and environmental change in yellow bellied marmots&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;am interested in the impact of climate changes on the  evolution of traits of yellow-bellied marmots. More specifically I will use a quantitative genetic approach to study changes in traits &amp;amp; distribution and variance due to changes in the environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;research-methods&#34;&gt;Research methods&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;long-term-monitoring&#34;&gt;Long-term monitoring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-term studies are the best way to track changes in the environment and quantify their consequences for population dynamics and fitness consequences of quantitative phenotypic traits, two key components of understanding the impacts of climate change. Although I highly value this approach to study ecological and evolutionary questions, it provides results that are correlative and not causative as one could obtain with an experiment. On the other hand, experimentation on life-history trade-offs or selection in the wild are nearly impossible when studying long-lived animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unmanned-aerial-vehicles-uavs&#34;&gt;Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UAVs offer the ability to collect new data non-invasively, and quite rapidly over a small to medium scale of the environment. I am mainly using aerial mappinig type of data to estiamte habitat quality and size, identity animals at the individual level and precisely map them. If a flight could fairly be quick, the post-processing of the data collected could be gigantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;statistics&#34;&gt;Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mixed model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;animal model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;random regression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;double hierarchical model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;path analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;social network analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;geostatistical analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;past-projects&#34;&gt;Past projects&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;orangutan-nest-watch&#34;&gt;Orangutan Nest Watch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We fly drones over an area of Forest in Sabah, Malaysian Borneo in order to find out how orangutans are affected by human impacts on their environment. Orangutans are Critically Endangered and it is vital to protect their remaining habitat. However we do not yet know at what population densities they live, so we need to search through each individual photo to see if we can find their nests and their vital food source- strangler fig trees. The more we know about the habitat orangutans can survive in, the more we can build to protect suitable areas of forest where they can live into the future, and reduce the threat of local extinction. Find out more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.journecology.com/orangutan-nest-survey&#34;&gt; project site &lt;/a&gt; but more importantly volunteer and help us by participating on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/sol-dot-milne/orangutan-nest-watch&#34;&gt;Zooniverse project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;spatial-and-social-structure-at-harbour-seal-haul-out-sites-using-unmanned-aerial-vehicles-uavs&#34;&gt;Spatial and social structure at harbour seal haul-out sites using Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am interested in the social structure and spatial distribution of seals at haul out sites. Due to heavy logistics, simple data such as individual body condition, distance between neighbours and identity of neighbour are rarely known in seal studies. Using UAVs, I am able to measure, identity and map precisely seals hauling out. I am looking at stabilty of social structure throughout the seasons and years, as well as habitat selection at small scale for haul out site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;personality-in-long-lived-fulmars-and-its-impact-on-foraging-strategies-and-reproduction&#34;&gt;Personality in long-lived fulmars and its impact on foraging strategies and reproduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a long-term study of fulmars at Eynhallow, Orkney Islands, UK, I am looking at the between individual variation in docility and agressiveness and their consequences on reproductive output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reproductive-strategies-of-bighorn-ewes&#34;&gt;Reproductive strategies of Bighorn ewes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my PhD, I worked on reproductive strategies of bighorn sheep females with Pr. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.usherbrooke.ca/mfesta/marco.htm&#34;&gt;Marco Festa-Bianchet&lt;/a&gt;. I was interested in how adult females allocate energy to reproduction or to survival under different conditions.  In few words, bighorn females always favor their own body condition and survival over the ones of their lambs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;personality-in-wild-eastern-chipmunk&#34;&gt;Personality in wild eastern chipmunk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have done my M.Sc on personality in wild chipmunks under the supervision of Pr. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unites.uqam.ca/crcec/indexEnglish.htm&#34;&gt;Denis Réale&lt;/a&gt;. My main interest was to establish if individuals differed in their behaviour in a stressful situation and how these differences were related to hormones and human disturbance&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
